Well, all right, let's talk about the
flurry of reform movements that sprang
up during the guilded age that aimed to
give the negative effects of industrial
capitalism a proper smack bottom. If
you're ready to get them brain cows
milk, then I stand at the ready to milk
them. Let's get to it. Okay, so I don't
think it's too much to say that some
Americans got real twitchy on account of
the rapid pace of change that came along
with industrialization in the second
half of the 19th century. There was
economic change with the rich getting
richer and the poor getting poor. There
was social change resulting from
urbanization and the rise of the middle
class. And then there was political
change with the federal government often
siding with big business against workers
and local governments being dominated by
political machines of which I'll have
much more to say in the next couple
videos. Anyway, the point is despite all
of its benefits, industrialization
messed a lot of people's crap up. And as
a general rule of history, the quicker
you mess people's crap up, the more
reactions it provokes. So now it's time
to consider five different groups of
Americans that put forth an alternative
vision for American progress. Each of
which challenge the social and economic
realities imposed by industrialization.
Oh, and by the way, if you want note
guys to follow along with this video and
all my videos, check that link in the
description. Anyway, the first group
that called for reform were agrarians,
which is to say the farmy farmy type
folk. Now, hopefully by now you've seen
a pattern throughout this whole course,
namely that when the US suffers
economically, it's usually the farmers
that feel at first. And the guilded age
was no exception to that rule. You see,
in the 1880s, international prices began
to decline precipitously for key
agricultural exports like wheat and
cotton. And as a result, farmers,
especially in the west and the south,
took on more and more debt until they
really had no hope of climbing out of
that hole. And farmers generally blamed
industrialization for the bulk of their
aggra misery. And that was for several
reasons. Like not only had the
commercialization of agriculture forced
many farmers out of business, but large
railroad companies on whom farmers and
ranchers depended to ship their goods to
market, often charged exorbitant prices
that left agrarians more than a little
saucy. And so in order to address these
issues, they organized various farmers
alliances, including the Northwestern
Farmers Alliance and the Southern
Farmers Alliance and the Colored Farmers
Alliance, the last of which was formed
because black farmers were not allowed
to join the other collectives. And then
by 1889, the three groups had joined
together and merged with the Knights of
Labor to form the National Farmers
Alliance and Industrial Union. And what
alternative vision says you did this
agrarian labor collective advocate for
the US? Well, says I, they used their
large membership to advocate for the
reduction of tariffs and government
ownership of railroads and the direct
election of senators. Additionally, they
advocated for an increase in the money
supply by adding more silver to the US
coinage. And if that happened, then
prices would rise and all the debt held
by farmers would be easier to pay off
with inflated currency. Now, ultimately,
the reforms advocated by these agrarians
weren't that successful yet, but later a
lot of the reforms would be picked up by
the Populist Party, and I'll tell you
about them in the next video. Okay. The
second group that advocated an
alternative vision for America were
utopians. Now, the word utopia describes
an imagined place in which everything is
perfect. And in case you haven't been
alive for more than 5 minutes, let me
assure you that such a place does not
exist. And in fact, utopia is derived
from a Greek word that literally means
no place. Anyway, some writers reacted
to the social and economic upheaval of
the guilded age by critiquing the
extravagance and materialism of the age
and ended up finding a wide readership.
And one of the best examples here is our
boy Edward Bellamy. So in 1880, Bellamy
published a novel called Looking
Backward, which portrayed industrialists
as wicked men who were responsible for
the slaughter of the working class. And
the main character falls asleep and then
wakes up in the year 2000 to find the
United States transformed into a
socialist utopia where all industries
are nationalized and therefore work for
the good of all people and not just a
few. And of course that's why Bellamy
was accused of being not just a
socialist but more to the point a
utopian because you know [laughter] that
is not how it went. Okay. And then the
third group who advanced an alternative
vision for America were the socialists.
For example, in 1879, Henry George
published a book called Progress in
Poverty, which was a biting criticism of
a society that enabled a few to become
wealthy beyond belief, while many at the
bottom could barely afford necessities
like food and housing. And by George's
reckoning, the main cause of this
problem was the arrangement of people
paying rent to landlords. Like, for the
most part, people who lived in squalor
could barely afford to pay their rent.
But in paying it, the owner of the land
and the building grew wealthier as the
value of the land increased. And so
George's solution was to advocate for a
single land tax which would neutralize
the advantage wealthy land owners had
over the renters because of the
increasing values of their land. And
then the fourth group that you're going
to need to know were devotees of the
social gospel which by definition refers
to a Christian movement whose members
attempted to reform industrial society
by making a careful application of
biblical principles to everyday life.
Additionally, social gospelers took
issue with those proponents of social
Darwinism who argued that poverty was
largely caused by the racial
deficiencies of the working class.
Instead, these folks argued that poverty
arose because of the fundamental
inequalities of the social environment
created by the government and big
business during the guilded age. So, an
early leader of this movement was a
congregationalist minister in Columbus,
Ohio named Washington Gladen. And in his
sermons and writings, Gladen advocated
for labor unions and business
regulations and better wages for workers
and condemned the lynching of black
Americans in the south. And those are
pretty saucy sermon topics if you ask
me. Anyway, to Gladen and the other
devotees of the social gospel, the
teachings of Christ were not applicable
only to individual salvation, but with
proper contextualization spoke also to
the most current problems facing
contemporary Christians. And finally,
the fifth group critiquing guilded age
social and economic issues were artists.
For example, Mark Twain published The
Adventures of Huckleberry Finn in 1884
in which he criticized industrial
America as filled with greed and
violence and racial discrimination. Or
another example, Jacob Reeves published
a book called How the Other Half Lives,
which is a combination of photographs
and essays that revealed the horrible
living conditions of the working poor.
So the photos showed in graphic detail
how the poor lived in shoddy,
overcrowded tenementss, and how those
conditions were profoundly unsafe and
unsanitary, leading to the rapid spread
of disease and the constant threat of
fire and other disasters. And as it
turned out, many of these groups
advocating for changes didn't see much
meaningful progress in the 19th century.
But a lot of these causes are going to
find some traction in the progressive
movement. But that's a story for unit 7.
Okay, so now let's consider how women
sought reform during this period. And
there are three big categories for their
efforts. First, women sought greater
equality with men by joining voluntary
organizations. So by the 1880s, women's
clubs devoted to social reform began
multiplying rapidly. And each group
focused on specific societal troubles
like urban pollution or poverty or the
working conditions of industrial
laborers. And by 1890, many of these
groups banded together under a larger
collective known as the General
Federation of Women's Club. Now, a
significant majority of the women who
joined these clubs were from the middle
class. And that's a big deal because
remember that middle-ass women during
this time were saddled with the social
expectations to remain in the home and
raise children and serve her lordly
husband. However, these reform-minded
women justified their foray into social
reform by invoking the idea of
maternalism. You see, the idea was that
just as children needed maternal care,
so too did a woman's neighborhood and
city need similar motherly attention.
And so by connecting their actions to
their assigned social role, these women
represented a kind of middle position
between the entirely domestic woman and
the woman demanding full equal rights
with men. And then the second way women
saw equality was by going to college in
increasing numbers. Though for the most
part they attended all women's schools.
And not surprisingly, so many women
enrolling for higher education got the
men folk all kinds of twitchy, not least
the medical men folk. Like doctors were
alarmed at all this fem education
because in their professional opinion,
too much learning would be harmful to
the female body. In fact, the doctors
argue that by devoting themselves to the
acquisition of knowledge, women would be
drawing energy to their brains away from
their ovaries, which would result in the
bearing of weak children. And I wish I
could tell you that this was some kind
of a joke to keep you entertained in a
YouTube video, but no, this was the
actual view of medical professionals who
purported to be scientists. Anyway, on
the other side of this debate, you had
longtime women's rights advocates like
Elizabeth Katie Stanton. She argued that
given the volatility of the rapidly
expanding and contracting economy, women
could not reliably depend on their
husbands and fathers to provide for
their needs. Therefore, an educated
woman would have far more opportunities
available to her and needed to pursue
that kind of self-improvement. And
finally, the third way women advocated
for equality with men was by promoting
social and political reform. So women
devoted themselves to all kinds of
reform efforts during this period, but
the largest and most visible was their
dedication to the temperance movement,
which aimed to eliminate the sale and
manufacture of alcohol in the United
States. Now, make no mistake,
drunkenness was a real problem among
urban male factory workers during this
period. And that was a large cause of
the growing impoverishment of the
working classes. And so to combat this,
women formed the Women's Christian
Temperance Union in 1874. And they
crusaded for total abstinence from
alcohol. And apparently it was a popular
message because they had something like
500,000 members on their roles by 1898.
Now this organization along with others
like the Anti- Saloon League worked
largely through peaceful means like
protest and trying to lobby Congress to
pass laws. But there was a more radical
strand of women who refused to wait for
the painfully slow gears of Congress to
turn. And maybe the best example I can
think of here is Carrie Nation. And she
said of herself that she was a bulldog
running at the feet of Jesus barking at
what he doesn't like. And apparently
Jesus didn't like alcohol because what
Carrie Nation was known for was her
hatchet which she carried into saloons
and hacked at liquor barrels until they
spilled their contents on the floor.
Carrie, you diva. And just like the
reformers I mentioned before, many of
the efforts of women's rights advocates
would face considerable opposition in
the last decades of the 19th century.
But they too would eventually taste the
fruit of their efforts during the
progressive era. But we're going to have
to save that for the next unit. Okay.
Click here to watch my other videos for
unit 6. Or you can click here to grab my
video note guides which are going to
help you get all the contents of this
course firmly crammed into your brain
folks. I'm glad you came by and I'll
catch on the flipflop.